<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-04T19:27:34+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mike’s words</title><subtitle>An eventually-cessant rambling. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Keyboards: Masochism in Disguise</title><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/keyboards-masochism-in-disguise/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keyboards: Masochism in Disguise"/><published>2024-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/keyboards:-masochism-in-disguise</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/keyboards-masochism-in-disguise/"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve ever learned a new language, you may have realised that doing so taught you so much about your mother tongue. Sentence structures, cases, tenses. These concepts leap from the subconscious mind into the critical part of your brain. Have you ever thought about how there’s even two ways to pronounce ‘the’, based on whether or not the following sound is a vowel or consonant.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p> <p>This article intends to spark a similar epiphany about a relatively mundane concept in comparison, the computer keyboard. You’ll learn how you’ve gotten used to the discomfort, and why it was so hard to learn to type when you were a child all those years ago.</p> <p>We’ll begin with the first typewriter, and incrementally improve until we have reached something <em>actually designed for the human hand</em>. We’ll minimise the likelihood and severity of <a href="https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/repetitive-strain-injury-rsi/">RSI</a>, and increase comfort while we’re at it.</p> <p>This article is written with the assumption that the reader is a standard home-row touch-typist, where the fingers rest on “ASDF” and “JKL;”. If you don’t type in this style, you will find much more comfort in learning this method than any improvement suggested below. I personally recommend <a href="https://www.typingclub.com">typingclub.com</a> as a great resource to learn.</p> <hr/> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/Sholes_typewriter-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/Sholes_typewriter-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/Sholes_typewriter-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/Sholes_typewriter.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" style=" max-width: 300px; " loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>The year is 1868. Americans Christopher Sholes, Frank Hall, Carlos Glidden and Samuel Soule patent the first typewriter, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sholes_and_Glidden_typewriter">Sholes and Glidden Typewriter</a>. It’s the first to have a QWERTY layout, and its commercial success causes QWERTY to become the de-facto standard layout for all following typewriters and keyboards<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This isn’t the only point I wish to flag - notably, the keys aren’t vertically aligned as there needs to be space to connect each button to its hammer with a metal rod.</p> <p>I’ll come back to QWERTY. Let’s address this vertical alignment for now. Your fingers will comfortably bend over 180 degrees along their length, but they don’t really go sideways. Feel free to try getting more than even a 50-degree range of motion, but I suggest you do so outside a hospital. My point is keys should be aligned in columns, so we avoid that making that awkward diagonal travel as much as possible. There’s also no real reason to have differently-sized buttons, so we can do away with those too. With both modifications, we have (re)invented the ortholinear keyboard:</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/grid-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/grid-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/grid-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/grid.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">An ortholinear keyboard built by <a href="https://mpilquist.github.io/blog/2017/07/22/building-a-planck-keyboard/" target="_blank">mpilquist</a>.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>We’re already at the point where things are looking very alien. But don’t worry, this rabbit hole goes <em>much</em> deeper! You may have noticed that the above keyboard is missing a number row, numpad, navigation cluster and function keys. That’s because this is a 40% keyboard, meaning the number of keys on the physical device is 40% of that of a traditional keyboard. We access those keys through a concept called <strong>layering</strong>.</p> <p>You’re already familiar with the idea, you just don’t know it. The shift key on your keyboard serves no purpose on its own, but holding it down changes the output of every other key on the device. Letters become capitalised, numbers are replaced with symbols and so on. We could say that by holding down the shift key, we are temporarily moving to the shift layer. Now, we extrapolate this idea. Imagine a second shift key, let’s call it ‘swap’. Much like shift it has no behaviour on its own, but modifies the behaviour of other keys. Swap + Q can be our ‘1’ key, swap + Y is ‘6’, you get the idea. Indeed this is exactly what the pictured keyboard is set up to do, you’ll note there is a swap (“raise”) key to the immediate right of the space bar. There’s also a “lower” key to the left. We can have an arbitrary number of layers, as long as we have a way to access them.</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/planck_layout-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/planck_layout-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/planck_layout-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/planck_layout.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Mpilquist's layout. Raise + k is '=', lower + t is '%'</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p><em>“But why bother with this?”</em>, you may find yourself asking. <em>“What’s wrong with having more buttons?”</em>. As I addressed at the top of this article, we are reducing the impact of RSI. If you’re one of the 60-80% of people in the developed world who primarily conduct their work at a computer, this impacts <strong>you</strong> and is a real health concern. You should be avoiding awkward finger movements. Having fewer buttons necessarily means everything can be closer to your resting home row position, and therefore more natural to reach. There’s certainly a balance to be struck, but the current standard is way off.</p> <p>So, in this pursuit to get rid of buttons, I’m going to make things even crazier. What if I told you we don’t need dedicated keys for shift, ctrl, alt &amp; friends? Enter <strong>hold-tap</strong> behaviour. It’s 2024, keyboards can be programmed to do different things if their keys are tapped, or held down<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. With this new dimension to expand in, we could make letters capitalise themselves if we hold the key for longer than 200 milliseconds. In practice, this would be slow, so let’s retain the idea of a shifting key, but simply put it on a letter key. For example, holding down the q key could capitalise every other letter key. We’d need a second one of these if we ever wanted a capital ‘Q’, so let’s put that on the other side of the keyboard, on P. We’ve now made the left and right shift keys redundant, and we can remove or repurpose these keys too. The next improvement is to actually do this with F and J, instead of Q and P, so we don’t even need to move our fingers to hit the shift key. We can do something similar with all of the home row. We’ll call these our ‘home row mods’:</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/home-row-mods-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/home-row-mods-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/home-row-mods-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/home-row-mods.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">A typical suite of home row mods that would be implemented using hold-tap behaviour</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>Let’s address wrist pain. It’s generally agreed that having your wrist bent outwards towards your pinky for an extended period is unhealthy. Easily done, just move the keys to your hand so you can reach all keys without bending your wrist.</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/ergonomic-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/ergonomic-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/ergonomic-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/ergonomic.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">A Logitech ERGO K860</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>There’s nothing stopping us from splitting the keyboard into two free halves that can be oriented however you wish.</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/split1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/split1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/split1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/split1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" style=" max-width: 550px; " loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">A Perixx PERIBOARD-624B</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>Let’s put it all together. A split keyboard, in an ortholinear layout with minimal numbers of keys:</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/split2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/split2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/split2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/split2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" style=" max-width: 550px; " loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">An Iris Rev. 8</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>I lied! That’s not ortholinear - the keys aren’t in a grid. This variant is called a column-staggered layout and takes into account the differing lengths and natural positions of your fingers. You’ll also notice the oddly placed buttons in the bottom corners. These are the thumb clusters. Placed to be as comfortable as possible to reach, this design gives your strongest finger more to do. The thumbs on a traditional keyboard are almost entirely wasted, used for space and maybe the occasional ctrl or alt press. We can place frequently-used keys like our backspace and enter here, taking these keys from being awkward to reach with your weakest finger, to being placed right under your thumb. Typically, layer keys are placed in the thumb clusters too.</p> <p>There’s only a couple easy improvements left to make before I begin my QWERTY slander. When bending your finger, your fingertip traces a curved path. Knowing this, let’s raise the furthest keys to construct a bowl shape, which means we need <em>even less</em> movement to reach further keys.</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/glove80-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/glove80-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/glove80-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/glove80.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">A MoErgo Glove80</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>And lastly, something called ‘tenting’. It’s not totally necessary and not everyone likes it, but you can raise the thumb side of the board to create a more natural angle for your hands to rest at.</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/glove80-tented-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/glove80-tented-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/glove80-tented-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/glove80-tented.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">A tented MoErgo Glove80</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>We’ve reached a point where the device pictured is barely recognisable as a keyboard. It looks more like something you’d pilot an alien spaceship with. Some take things to the extreme, with blank keycaps or attaching the things to your armrests. There’s a lot of experimentation to be done, and everyone’s optimal setup is going to be different.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="why-qwerty-sucks">Why QWERTY sucks</h2> <p>In the English language, the three most common letters are E, T and A. In the QWERTY layout, you need to move your fingers to reach these keys. Meanwhile, K and J respectively make the 5th and 4th least-used letters, yet for some reason these live on the home row. Madness. I do not wish to even comment on the semicolon key, for I cannot do so without a lot of impassioned swearing.</p> <p>55% of typing is done on the top row, while the home row only sees 30%. <em>Over two-thirds of the time, you need to move your finger to a different row hit the key you want.</em> Cumulatively, the seven QWERTY letter keys that your fingers rest on comprise 26% of your typing. To give you a sense of just how bad that is, if we set these 7 keys to just be the top 7 most frequent letters instead, we get up to 58%! Moving the semicolon key elsewhere, we can add another letter, reaching 64%. Yes, it’s possible that two-thirds of your typing can be done without moving.</p> <p>There are other optimisations to consider though. For example, we want to minimise making one finger do a disproportionate amount of work when typing a single word. Consider the word ‘unjust’, four of the six requisite keypresses are done by the same finger. Also, we want common two-letter sequences (“bigram”) to be comfortable to type. For example, it would be unacceptable to have to type Q and U, or T and H with the same finger. There are a lot of metrics to consider. This stuff gets very complicated - for example, the sequence ‘ll’ is disproportionately common when compared to the relative frequency of the letter L itself. That is to say, it is weirdly common for ‘L’s to appear in pairs when analysing all ‘L’s in typical English. Does that mean we should put L in a more accessible location?</p> <p>Luckily, a lot of very clever people have already done this difficult analysis for us. There is a whole world of alternative keyboard layouts, but the most prevalent are Dvorak and Colemak (and its popular variant, Colemak Mod-DH).</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2024-10-04/colemak-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/colemak-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2024-10-04/colemak-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2024-10-04/colemak.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">A typical Colemak layout.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>You’ll immediately notice that the most common letters have been moved to the middle row, but we retain the convenience of common shortcut keys remaining in place in the lower left (ctrl-z and friends). Another improvement to note, the relatively useless caps lock key has been replaced with a second backspace, which is more easily reached than a typical backspace.</p> <p>The biggest drawback to this is that you already know QWERTY and relearning muscle memory is hard. It can take weeks, months or even years to get to the point where you are as comfortable on a new layout as you were on QWERTY. Even worse, in doing so you can lose competence on normal layouts. It’s certainly not for everyone. Me? I’m learning Colemak-DH, and will eventually switch to it full-time. It’s extremely infuriating, but by god is it so much more comfortable.</p> <hr/> <p>There are dozens of behaviours you can assign to keys. Hundreds of standard keyboard layouts. Thousands of differently-shaped keyboards. I hope I’ve helped you realise just how badly typing sucks currently, and I hope I have given you the courage to break free from its carpal tunnel-strained grip.</p> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>“The paper, the alphabet. The dog, the oven.” It’s not totally ubiquitous, but most speakers will say something more like ‘thee’ when preceding a vowel sound to avoid the mildly uncomfortable glottal stop. Man, I totally would have studied linguistics if I wasn’t into computers. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>There are competing theories as to exactly how and why the QWERTY layout was invented. <a href="https://repository.kulib.kyoto-u.ac.jp/dspace/bitstream/2433/139379/1/42_161.pdf">This paper</a> aims to explore the real reasoning. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote"> <p>At time of writing, complex behaviour like this is usually achieved with either QMK or ZMK keyboard firmware. <a href="https://zmk.dev/docs/keymaps/behaviors/hold-tap">Here’s</a> the ZMK documentation for hold-tap. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An exploration of how they can be so, so much better.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Company Disloyalty</title><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/company-disloyalty/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Company Disloyalty"/><published>2024-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/company-disloyalty</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/company-disloyalty/"><![CDATA[<p>During interviews for a job in March, I made clear I was looking for a long-term role. One I could really sink my teeth into and grow as an engineer. I got on well with my interviewers, and indeed got the job, starting in April. September comes along, and I’m made redundant. No warning, just pulled into a meeting with HR, my boss, and my boss’s boss to be told my job no longer exists<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, about a week after a stellar performance review. Such is the way of the startup. At least you’d think, right? This is the second time in twelve months I have been made redundant; I experienced the same exact thing at a large transnational corporation in November.</p> <p>I’m not writing this to whine. As the headline suggests, I want to discuss the expectations one should have in the working world, both as an employer and employee<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Company loyalty in its traditional form is foolish. Much like a relationship with a romantic partner, there is a continuous expectation for your end of the bargain to be held. If it’s your job to take the bins out every week, you can expect consequences if you stop doing that. As this extends to the requirements of one’s role, it does to the requirements of the employer. Anti-WFH return to office initiatives, stagnation of pay and seniority, responsibility creep. These things all contribute to high turnover, and for good reason. But the opposite is also true. Job hunting is stressful and frustrating, and merely a stark minority would choose to hop between roles if they truly appreciated their position &amp; progress trajectory.</p> <p>The ideal employee is proactive, takes initiative, and truly finds pride in their work, striving to improve life for others, be they colleagues, customers or otherwise. The ideal employer catalyses this, rewarding exemplary behaviour with pay increases, seniority, and a healthy dose of challenge to occupy the brain. If either party fails to deliver, the relationship will not last. Redundancies break this rule, and have seen many a fruitful employment end prematurely, for arcane macroscopic reasons like ‘market conditions’ and ‘organisational restructuring’.</p> <p>Know your worth as someone who creates value. Do not get comfortable in stagnation. Spark a carnal desire within you to be rewarded fairly for your work.</p> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>If you’ve not (yet) had the misfortune of experiencing a layoff meeting, you won’t know just how brutal they can be. Expect to hear things like: “This decision is not up for negotiation.” “We wish you luck.” etc. If this takes place in an office, you will be greeted by security as you leave the meeting room, who will helpfully offer to show you the way out of the building. They’ll even generously look after your company ID card - you know, the one required to enter the building. Remote working instead? Within seconds after the Zoom call ends, your company-provided laptop will lock you out, and your personal GitHub account will be removed from the company’s organisation. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>I speak only for the world of software engineering. Translate as appropriate for your line of work. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the myth of the devoted employee.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Action Precedes Motivation</title><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/action-precedes-motivation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Action Precedes Motivation"/><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/action-precedes-motivation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/action-precedes-motivation/"><![CDATA[<p>I often think about the fleeting nature of motivation. I catch myself waiting for it to arrive, like I might await a bus.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-additive-identity">The Additive Identity</h2> <p>It’s common for me to feel the most motivated during a long, hard day at my job. Equally, it’s hard for me to get into the working mood if the clock strikes ten and I haven’t yet sunk my teeth into something big.</p> <p>Rarely will you want to start cooking, but once you’ve started you’ll find it’s less effort than you thought; perhaps even enjoyable. Emptying the kitchen bin is a chore, but as you walk that stinking bag outside you might notice you don’t mind moving around &amp; getting some fresh air. How many times have you dreaded mowing the lawn, only to be disappointed it’s over so soon?</p> <p>I speak in literals for sake of illustration. Some chores you will always hate, no matter what. Others will have you arguing they’re not chores at all. My point addresses those middle-of-the-road mundane must-dos of modern life, whatever they may be for you.</p> <p>Your mind has many functions. Two are ‘work’ and ‘play’. It is easy to continue working once started, and trivial to extend play. Switching between the two is difficult, and requires some level of willpower. Observe that motivation is a productivity multiplier, and it never arrives in the absence of said productivity.</p> <h2 id="the-curse-of-the-infinite-scroll">The Curse of the Infinite Scroll</h2> <p>The smartphone is one of the single most groundbreaking inventions. Ever. A close second being humorous juxtaposition. It’s the modern multi-tool, and a byproduct of this is the thinning &amp; erasure of the line between work and play. Picture this - you’re writing an import email to a colleague. Ping! A notification from Facebook tells you that a friend commented on a post. Opening it out of habit, you see that Geoff has commented one of his friends’ names below a video of an AI-generated bird. You don’t care, and in fact, you haven’t spoken to Geoff in years. Instinctively, you scroll. A video of a man falling over. An advert for a handbag on a Chinese drop-shipping site. A carousel of the same five suggested friends that Facebook has been showing you for weeks. You scroll on.</p> <p>Fifteen minutes have passed, and you suddenly snap out of a stupor you were unaware you were in. At no point in the last fifteen minutes did Facebook add any value to your life. You now feel sluggish and unmotivated, a byproduct of crashing from the high dopamine release Facebook is designed to foist upon your body. Indeed, this isn’t your fault. Social media companies employ rooms full of people to design interfaces that boost the chance of you accidentally clicking on an advert, or other equally dubious outcomes that <a href="https://www.wheresyoured.at/were-watching-facebook-die/">Ed Zitron covers in a much more articulate way than I ever could</a>.</p> <p><em>“That email still needs writing,”</em> you contemplate. <em>“I’ll do it later.”</em></p> <p>Take some time to form a plan or routine that rebuilds the conceptual wall between work and play, especially in the context of using your mobile phone. Perhaps only allow yourself to use social media applications between the hours of 18:00 and 20:00. Or set a screen time limit. You have options, and taking action now may improve your life significantly.</p> <hr/> <p>Instead of awaiting that bus, just start walking. Find it within you to <strong>just start</strong>, and motivation will find you, and help you along the way.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Facebook stops you getting out of bed in the morning.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beauty in Detail</title><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/beauty-in-detail/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty in Detail"/><published>2024-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/beauty-in-detail</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/beauty-in-detail/"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever looked at something? Not just glanced at it, but really, <em>really</em>, looked at something? Try it right now. Look at the tip of a single finger. Go on. I’ll still be here when you’re done.</p> <hr/> <p>I hope you took some time to do so. I hope you noticed the imperfect, and the irregular. Perhaps you found a scar you never knew about, or the tiniest speck of dirt that you must have picked up in the ten minutes since you last washed your hands. Or maybe you just took the time to marvel at the uniqueness of your fingerprint. Were there swirls or straight lines? Is it nearly symmetrical or is it rather picassian?</p> <p>Everything has detail if only you choose to look for it. The paint on your walls. The arrangement of hairs on your head. The cheese on your pizza. There is no such thing as ‘smooth’ in the real world, nor do the man-made concepts of ‘uniform’, ‘equal’, ‘flat’, or ‘consistent’ instil any sanity in the madness of the universe. Try to comprehend the sheer unadulterated chaos that surrounds you all the time. Every single time you rip a piece of paper, you create a unique, never-before-seen pattern of bumps and ridges. I think there’s something beautiful in that.</p> <p>The next time you walk down the street, try to look for things you’ve never seen before. Within seconds you’ll find a road marking you never noticed is wearing away, or a small grey box on the side of a building, the function of which you’ll never know.</p> <p>The next time you’re bored and reaching for your phone, try instead to see something new in the world.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Everything's a fractal.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Writing About Writing</title><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/writing-about-writing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing About Writing"/><published>2024-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/writing-about-writing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/writing-about-writing/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve toyed with the idea of writing for a while. And by a while, I in truth mean a week or two. If you think that isn’t a long time, that’s because you’re right - but I ask which is better, to do everything on a whim the moment I want to, or to wait and ensure the current thing isn’t an impulsive lurch of motivation that will vanish as abruptly as it appeared? I digress. I decided today to get to it. Translation? I spent all morning today getting GitHub pages to play nicely with Jekyll. But the end result of this is that I can just write nice, simple Markdown. Indeed, I’m writing Markdown right now in VS Code and when I commit and push this, the webpage you are currently looking at will be generated. Lovely.</p> <p>I’m writing this post because I want to explore and formalise my thoughts about why I want to write. The intention of this page is different to others; it serves as a journey, one which at the destination I hope to be closer to knowing <em>why</em> I am doing this.</p> <hr/> <p>There’s no best place to begin, so why not start with inspiration. Ed Zitron is currently my favourite writer, with his <a href="https://www.wheresyoured.at">Where’s Your Ed At</a> blog brimming with cutting insights into the world of tech. His work helps me feel like I’m informed about an industry I care about, told from a perspective of healthy scepticism. Other personal favourites include Peter Welch of <a href="https://www.stilldrinking.org/essays.php">Still Drinking</a> and Ethan Dalool of <a href="https://voussoir.net/writing">voussoir.net</a>. I admire how these people possess the skill and confidence to put quality writing out into the world, about whatever they wish to. I hope to one day add value into the world in the way these people do, even if my audience ends up relegated to small group of programmers on their lunch breaks, who are putting off getting up and making a sandwich. <em>I see you.</em></p> <p>I realise now that <strong>I’m doing this for me.</strong> I like writing<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. It’s good exercise for the brain, and it serves as a constructive way for me to hurl words at the world. It’s always nice to be able to point at something and say “I made that.” As a career software engineer, there are a good few projects I can say I contributed to, and many more that I would never admit to. But these are transient. They’re products that come and go, websites that are never deployed, and data-flow architectures that nobody will ever give a shit about. Words are real, made for people and not compilers. Years from now, I can look back on this and appreciate what I made, without having to worry about an outdated toolchain or missing imports.</p> <p>I want to be a better writer. I want to train my mind to produce colourful imagery, to wield the keyboard as a paintbrush, putting not words into a document, but ideas into a reader’s mind.</p> <p>I’m not doing this for money. I have a job for that. There are no adverts on this site. It doesn’t give you annoying pop-ups about cookies. Nor does it collect any data about you (besides whatever GitHub Pages does itself). There’s no SEO, logo, nor art bar a favicon I generated in 30 seconds. I do not and will never know the readership numbers of this site, because I don’t want to know. No comments, likes or share buttons. Creating this cost me nothing but my time, and I expect nothing in return.</p> <hr/> <p>So, what can you as a reader expect from this blog? Unreliable post frequency, dubious quality and a smattering of subject matters of which probability dictates you will care about a minority at best. But, against all odds, there remains the small possibility of someone enjoying my work.</p> <p>And that chance alone makes this all worth it.</p> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>I haven’t always liked writing. In fact, I hated it as a child. I could never write enough, and this had my English teachers hounding me for lazily not reaching word counts. The gods themselves tremble before the blunt concision of a story written by seven-year-old Mike. But the truth is I wasn’t lazy, I just said all I felt needed to be said in fewer words than most, perhaps at the expense of the occasional metaphor or adjectival phrase. This changed when I reached university, and I went from writing stories to writing reports. Equally, the person reviewing my work went from the school’s Head of English to one of a few researchers who clearly considered it beneath them to pore over paragraph after paragraph of their students’ work. Suddenly, saying exactly what needed to be said and not a word more was a virtue, and I thrived for exactly the same behaviours that earned me detentions a decade prior. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Words about words.]]></summary></entry></feed>