<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-22T22:08:12+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mike’s words</title><subtitle>An eventually-cessant rambling. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Action Precedes Motivation</title><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/action-precedes-motivation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Action Precedes Motivation"/><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/action-precedes-motivation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/action-precedes-motivation/"><![CDATA[<p>I often think about the fleeting nature of motivation. I catch myself waiting for it to arrive, like I might await a bus.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-additive-identity">The Additive Identity</h2> <p>It’s common for me to feel the most motivated during a long, hard day at my job. Equally, it’s hard for me to get into the working mood if the clock strikes ten and I haven’t yet sunk my teeth into something big.</p> <p>Rarely will you want to start cooking, but once you’ve started you’ll find it’s less effort than you thought; perhaps even enjoyable. Emptying the kitchen bin is a chore, but as you walk that stinking bag outside you might notice you don’t mind moving around &amp; getting some fresh air. How many times have you dreaded mowing the lawn, only to be disappointed it’s over so soon?</p> <p>I speak in literals for sake of illustration. Some chores you will always hate, no matter what. Others will have you arguing they’re not chores at all. My point addresses those middle-of-the-road mundane must-dos of modern life, whatever they may be for you.</p> <p>Your mind has many functions. Two are ‘work’ and ‘play’. It is easy to continue working once started, and trivial to extend play. Switching between the two is difficult, and requires some level of willpower. Observe that motivation is a productivity multiplier, and it never arrives in the absence of said productivity.</p> <h2 id="the-curse-of-the-infinite-scroll">The Curse of the Infinite Scroll</h2> <p>The smartphone is one of the single most groundbreaking inventions, ever. A close second being humorous juxtaposition. It’s the modern multi-tool, and a byproduct of this is the thinning &amp; erasure of the line between work and play. Picture this - you’re writing an import email to a colleague. Ping! A notification from Facebook tells you that a friend commented on a post. Opening it out of habit, you see that Geoff has commented one of his friends’ names below a video of an AI-generated bird. You don’t care, and in fact, you haven’t spoken to Geoff in years. Instinctively, you scroll. A video of a man falling over. An advert for a handbag on a Chinese drop-shipping site. A carousel of the same five suggested friends that Facebook has been showing you for weeks. You scroll on.</p> <p>Fifteen minutes have passed, and you suddenly snap out of a stupor you were unaware you were in. At no point in the last fifteen minutes did Facebook add any value to your life. You now feel sluggish and unmotivated, a byproduct of crashing from the high dopamine release Facebook is designed to foist upon your body. Indeed, this isn’t your fault. Social media companies employ rooms full of people to design interfaces that boost the chance of you accidentally clicking on an advert, or other equally dubious outcomes that <a href="https://www.wheresyoured.at/were-watching-facebook-die/">Ed Zitron covers in a much more articulate way than I ever could</a>.</p> <p><em>“That email still needs writing,”</em> you contemplate. <em>“I’ll do it later.”</em></p> <p>Take some time to form a plan or routine that rebuilds the conceptual wall between work and play, especially in the context of using your mobile phone. Perhaps only allow yourself to use social media applications between the hours of 18:00 and 20:00. Or set a screen time limit. You have options, and taking action now may improve your life significantly.</p> <hr/> <p>Instead of awaiting that bus, just start walking. Find it within you to <strong>just start</strong>, and motivation will find you, and help you along the way.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Facebook stops you getting out of bed in the morning.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beauty in Detail</title><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/beauty-in-detail/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty in Detail"/><published>2024-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/beauty-in-detail</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/beauty-in-detail/"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever looked at something? Not just glanced at it, but really, <em>really</em>, looked at something? Try it right now. Look at the tip of a single finger. Go on. I’ll still be here when you’re done.</p> <hr/> <p>I hope you took some time to do so. I hope you noticed the imperfect, and the irregular. Perhaps you found a scar you never knew about, or the tiniest speck of dirt that you must have picked up in the ten minutes since you last washed your hands. Or maybe you just took the time to marvel at the uniqueness of your fingerprint. Were there swirls or straight lines? Is it nearly symmetrical or is it rather picassian?</p> <p>Everything has detail if only you choose to look for it. The paint on your walls. The arrangement of hairs on your head. The cheese on your pizza. There is no such thing as ‘smooth’ in the real world, nor do the man-made concepts of ‘uniform’, ‘equal’, ‘flat’, or ‘consistent’ instil any sanity in the madness of the universe. Try to comprehend the sheer unadulterated chaos that surrounds you all the time. Every single time you rip a piece of paper, you create a unique, never-before-seen pattern of bumps and ridges. I think there’s something beautiful in that.</p> <p>The next time you walk down the street, try to look for things you’ve never seen before. Within seconds you’ll find a road marking you never noticed is wearing away, or a small grey box on the side of a building, the function of which you’ll never know.</p> <p>The next time you’re bored and reaching for your phone, try instead to see something new in the world.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Everything's a fractal.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Writing About Writing</title><link href="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/writing-about-writing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing About Writing"/><published>2024-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/writing-about-writing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michael-ryan.github.io/blog/writing-about-writing/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve toyed with the idea of writing for a while. And by a while, I in truth mean a week or two. If you think that isn’t a long time, that’s because you’re right - but I ask which is better, to do everything on a whim the moment I want to, or to wait and ensure the current thing isn’t an impulsive lurch of motivation that will vanish as abruptly as it appeared? I digress. I decided today to get to it. Translation? I spent all morning today getting GitHub pages to play nicely with Jekyll. But the end result of this is that I can just write nice, simple Markdown. Indeed, I’m writing Markdown right now in VS Code and when I commit and push this, the webpage you are currently looking at will be generated. Lovely.</p> <p>I’m writing this post because I want to explore and formalise my thoughts about why I want to write. The intention of this page is different to others; it serves as a journey, one which at the destination I hope to be closer to knowing <em>why</em> I am doing this.</p> <hr/> <p>There’s no best place to begin, so why not start with inspiration. Ed Zitron is currently my favourite writer, with his <a href="https://www.wheresyoured.at">Where’s Your Ed At</a> blog brimming with cutting insights into the world of tech. His work helps me feel like I’m informed about an industry I care about, told from a perspective of healthy scepticism. Other personal favourites include Peter Welch of <a href="https://www.stilldrinking.org/essays.php">Still Drinking</a> and Ethan Dalool of <a href="https://voussoir.net/writing">voussoir.net</a>. I admire how these people possess the skill and confidence to put quality writing out into the world, about whatever they wish to. I hope to one day add value into the world in the way these people do, even if my audience ends up relegated to small group of programmers on their lunch breaks, who are putting off getting up and making a sandwich. <em>I see you.</em></p> <p>I realise now that <strong>I’m doing this for me.</strong> I like writing<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. It’s good exercise for the brain, and it serves as a constructive way for me to hurl words at the world. It’s always nice to be able to point at something and say “I made that.” As a career software engineer, there are a good few projects I can say I contributed to, and many more that I would never admit to. But these are transient. They’re products that come and go, websites that are never deployed, and data-flow architectures that nobody will ever give a shit about. Words are real, made for people and not compilers. Years from now, I can look back on this and appreciate what I made, without having to worry about an outdated toolchain or missing imports.</p> <p>I want to be a better writer. I want to train my mind to produce colourful imagery, to wield the keyboard as a paintbrush, putting not words into a document, but ideas into a reader’s mind.</p> <p>I’m not doing this for money. I have a job for that. There are no adverts on this site. It doesn’t give you annoying pop-ups about cookies. Nor does it collect any data about you (besides whatever GitHub Pages does itself). There’s no SEO, logo, nor art bar a favicon I generated in 30 seconds. I do not and will never know the readership numbers of this site, because I don’t want to know. No comments, likes or share buttons. Creating this cost me nothing but my time, and I expect nothing in return.</p> <hr/> <p>So, what can you as a reader expect from this blog? Unreliable post frequency, dubious quality and a smattering of subject matters of which probability dictates you will care about a minority at best. But, against all odds, there remains the small possibility of someone enjoying my work.</p> <p>And that chance alone makes this all worth it.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>I haven’t always liked writing. In fact, I hated it as a child. I could never write enough, and this had my English teachers hounding me for lazily not reaching word counts. The gods themselves tremble before the blunt concision of a story written by seven-year-old Mike. But the truth is I wasn’t lazy, I just said all I felt needed to be said in fewer words than most, perhaps at the expense of the occasional metaphor or adjectival phrase. This changed when I reached university, and I went from writing stories to writing reports. Equally, the person reviewing my work went from the school’s Head of English to one of a few researchers who clearly considered it beneath them to pore over paragraph after paragraph of their students’ work. Suddenly, saying exactly what needed to be said and not a word more was a virtue, and I thrived for exactly the same behaviours that earned me detentions a decade prior. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Words about words.]]></summary></entry></feed>